{"tossups": [{"question": "This island's Great Tulip Tree in Inwood Hill Park was the site of a celebration commemorating Robert Fulton and a certain 1609 discovery. The Castello Plan, created by Jacques Cortelyou, mapped a portion of this island while under Dutch settlement. A large statue of King George III was pulled down on this island's Bowling Green park, and this island was purchased for New Netherland from the Canarsee by Peter Minuit. New Amsterdam was founded on, for ten points, what densely populated island in New York City?", "answer": "<b><u>Manhattan</u></b> Island", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Two answers required: During a battle between these two countries, Raimondo Montecuccoli claimed, \"Today died a man who did honor to mankind\u201d after that man was killed by a cannonball. The Barrier Treaties were signed by these two countries, one of which invaded the other during the <em>Rampjaar</em> [[RAMP-yahr]]. A conflict between these two countries that led to a number of peripheral conflicts was ended with the Peace of Nijmegen [[NYE-may-gen]] signed in one of them. For ten points, name these two countries which were respectively led by Louis XIV [[the Fourteenth]] and William of Orange.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>France</u></b> and the <b><u>Netherlands</u></b> (accept <b><u>Holland</u></b> or <b><u>Nederland</u></b> in place of the \u201cNetherlands\u201d; accept Royaume de <b><u>France</u></b> in place of Kingdom of <b><u>France</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man served as governor of Cyprus before being elected tribune in 62 BC. This member of the <em>Optimates</em> was notoriously resistant to bribes and accused his rival of being a part of the Catiline Conspiracy. One anecdote from that rivalry involved this man publicly reading a love letter from his half-sister, Servilia. An opponent of the First Triumvirate, for ten points, who was this Roman senator and rival of Julius Caesar, the great-grandson of an orator known for ending speeches with the line, \"Carthage must be destroyed\"?", "answer": "<b><u>Cato the Younger</u></b> (or <b><u>Cato Minor</u></b>; accept Marcus Porcius <b><u>Cato Uticensis</u></b>; prompt on \u201cCato\u201d or \u201cMarcus Porcius Cato\u201d; do not accept or prompt on \"Cato the Elder\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "H.F. van Emden and David Peakall wrote a 1996 follow-up to this work titled: <em>Beyond</em> [this book]. This book was inspired by a letter appearing in <em>The Boston Herald</em> and credits declining bird populations to thin eggshells that broke prematurely. Al Gore credited this work with starting his interest in environmental issues, and this work was instrumental in the EPA's eventual ban on DDT for agricultural use. For ten points, name this best-selling 1962 environmental science book by Rachel Carson.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Silent Spring</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "In a Dutch town, two members of this organization named Sigismund Best and Richard Stevens were captured during the Venlo Incident after a trap was sprung by Abwehr [[AHB-vehr]] head Walter Schellenberg. This organization plotted, but never executed, a plan to sneak estrogen into Adolf Hitler's food in an effort to feminize him. Author Graham Greene served in this organization under Kim Philby, who later betrayed this organization as a member of the \"Cambridge Five\" and joined the KGB. For ten points, name this foreign intelligence agency of the United Kingdom.", "answer": "<b><u>MI6</u></b> (accept <b><u>Secret Intelligence Service</u></b>; accept <b><u>SIS</u></b>; prompt on \"Secret Service Bureau\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man and his sibling used Frank Meyer's principle of \"fusionism\" when they developed the \"Sharon Statement,\" which was the guiding thesis of the Young Americans for Freedom. This man threated to \"sock a\" debate opponent \"in the mouth\" if he kept calling him a crypto-Nazi during a publicly televised debate. Leftist intellectual Gore Vidal debated, for ten points, what intellectual conservative and host of <em>Firing Line</em> who founded the <em>National Review</em>?", "answer": "William F(rank) <b><u>Buckley</u></b>, Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Between 1854 and 1855, three of these events named Tokai, Nankai, and Edo were collectively known as the Ansei. The military murdered an estimated 6,000 Koreans and socialists who they believed caused one of these events. Goto Shinpei led infrastructure projects following a 1923 example of these events, which mostly did not impact Frank Lloyd Wright's Imperial Hotel. For ten points, name these natural disasters that included the Great Kanto, which destroyed many buildings in Japan.", "answer": "<b><u>Earthquake</u></b>s (accept 1923 Great Kanto <b><u>earthquake</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The first superintendent of an institution under this organization, Franklin Buchanan, defected to the Confederacy, and an academy run by this organization was established by George Bancroft. This organization's technology during the War of 1812 was analyzed in the first book by Theodore Roosevelt, who was this organization's Assistant Secretary. Alfred Thayer Mahan's time as an officer in this organization inspired his book <em>The Influence of Sea Power upon History</em>. For ten points, name this organization, which operates an Academy in Annapolis, Maryland.", "answer": "United States <b><u>Navy</u></b> (accept <b><u>USN</u></b>; prompt on \"United States Naval Academy\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An anachronism in a film about this historical figure involved the appearance of a pair of purple Converse sneakers during a shopping spree. A musical by Michael Kunze and Sylvester Levay parallels the life of this historical figure with a woman named Margrid Arnaud. A 2006 film directed by Sofia Coppola portrayed this figure\u2019s affair with Axel von Fersen. For ten points, what historical figure was the wife of Louis XVI [[the Sixteenth]] and last queen of France before the French Revolution?", "answer": "<b><u>Marie Antoinette</u></b> (or <b><u>Marie Antoinette</u></b> Jos\u00e8phe Jeanne; or <b><u>Maria Antonia</u> </b>Josepha Johanna)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "Geraldine Brooks's novel <em>March</em> analyses a father who has left to serve in this war as described in another book. Michael Shaara's <em>The Killer Angels</em> takes place during a battle in this war, a deserter from which is the subject of Charles Frazier's <em>Cold Mountain</em>. John Winder helped oversee a location used during this war in a novel by Mackinlay Kantor titled <em>Andersonville</em>. In a short novel, Henry Fleming overcomes his cowardice by seeking the title injury during this war. For ten points, name this war, the setting of <em>The Red Badge of</em> <em>Courage</em>.", "answer": "American <b><u>Civil War</u></b> (or United States <b><u>Civil War</u></b>; or U.S. <b><u>Civil War</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "A photograph at Sri Lanka\u2019s Palaly Airport shows this man being given a garland by an athlete. An anti-religion campaign may have led to the false attribution of a quote to this man in which he supposedly said that he \u201cdidn\u2019t see any God\u201d during his most famous undertaking. A MiG-15 crash killed this man, who once served at Luostari Air Base. This backup crew member of Soyuz 1 was best-known for a single 1961 orbit. For ten points, name this Soviet cosmonaut and first man in space.", "answer": "Yuri <b><u>Gagarin</u></b> (or Yuri Alexeyivich <b><u>Gagarin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "While speaking with Morley Safer, this figure controversially revealed that she would not be surprised if her eighteen-year old daughter admitted to having an affair. That interview prompted this woman\u2019s husband to say, \u201cWell, honey, there goes about 20 million votes.\u201d This prominent supporter of the Equal Rights Amendment co-founded a facility in Rancho Mirage for people suffering from drug addiction. Rising to her most prominent position in 1974, for ten points, who was this woman who succeeded Pat Nixon as First Lady?", "answer": "<b><u>B</u></b>etty <b><u>Ford</u></b> (prompt on \u201cFord\u201d; accept <b><u>E</u></b>lizabeth Anne <b><u>Ford</u></b>; accept <b><u>E</u></b>lizabeth Anne <b><u>Warren</u></b>; or <b><u>Elizabeth</u></b> Anne <b><u>Bloomer</u></b>; or <b><u>Betty Warren</u></b>; or <b><u>Betty Bloomer</u></b>; prompt on \u201cMs. Ford\u201d or similar answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One member of this family wrote <em>Geography Made Easy</em>, which became one of the most influential geography textbooks in the early United States. A son of this family\u2019s aforementioned member named Jedediah received guidance from Leonard Gale that allowed for his realization of a regular relay system to accomplish one task. The question \u201cWhat hath God wrought?\u201d was asked by a member of this family who developed the single-wire variant of a communications system. For ten points, what family included the telegraphy pioneer Samuel?", "answer": "<b><u>Morse</u></b> (accept Jedediah <b><u>Morse</u></b>; accept Samuel F(inley) B(reese) <b><u>Morse</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Daniel E. Nijensohn did an analysis of this person\u2019s skull x-rays and suggested that she was given a pre-frontal lobotomy months before her death. Thousands of people were injured when this person\u2019s body was transported to the Ministry of Labour Building. This person\u2019s corpse was found in a crypt in Milan, Italy under the name \u201cMar\u00eda Maggi\u201d after being lost for sixteen years following her husband's overthrow in the <em>Revoluci\u00f3n</em> <em>Libertadora</em>. For ten points, name this wildly popular first lady of Argentina during the late 1940s and early 1950s.", "answer": "<b><u>E</u></b>va <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b> (or Mar\u00eda <b><u>E</u></b>va Duarte de <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b>; or Mar\u00eda <b><u>Eva Duarte</u></b>; accept <b><u>E</u></b>vita <b><u>Per\u00f3n</u></b>; prompt on \u201cEvita\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "With the Offields, this family established the Catalina Island Conservancy. The character Walter Harvey, in <em>A League of Their Own</em>, may have been inspired by a member of this family who founded the All-American Girls Professional Baseball League during World War Two. Charles Weeghman facilitated the sale of an organization to this family, which names a location containing a wall covered in ivy. The Steve Bartman incident occurred at a location named for this family of chewing gum magnates. For ten points, the Chicago Cubs play in what family\u2019s namesake field?", "answer": "<b><u>Wrigley</u></b> (accept William Mills <b><u>Wrigley</u></b> Jr.; accept Philip Knight <b><u>Wrigley</u></b>; accept P.K. <b><u>Wrigley</u></b>; accept <b><u>Wrigley</u></b> Field)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "A replication of one of this psychologist\u2019s experiments used emails to study attitudes towards presidential candidate Ross Perot [[PEH-roh]]. The University of London replicated this psychologist\u2019s experiment on altruism by leaving 300 letters on sidewalks. This psychologist asked, \u201cCould it be that Eichmann and his million accomplices in the Holocaust were just following orders?\u201d in a noted namesake experiment. For ten points, what psychologist tested obedience to authority through the administering of fake electric shocks?", "answer": "Stanley <b><u>Milgram</u></b> (accept <b><u>Milgram</u></b> experiment(s))", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s son, with Kathleen Bruce, founded the World Wide Fund for Nature. This man claimed that his group would \u201cbow to the will of Providence\u201d in a \u201cMessage to the Public.\" A line from Alfred, Lord Tennyson\u2019s poem \u201cUlysses\u201d was inscribed in a monument built for those lost during this man\u2019s disastrous Terra Nova Expedition. That entry was written after this man\u2019s team descended Beardmore Glacier during an effort in which he learned that Roald Amundsen had already reached the South Pole. For ten points, name this British explorer of Antarctica.", "answer": "Robert Falcon <b><u>Scott</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Though not primarily known as a painter, this man created an oil work on canvas depicting <em>The Ruins of Holyrood Chapel</em>. Charles Marie Bouton [[boo-TOHN]] worked with this man who utilized \u201chypo,\" now known as sodium thiosulfate, to achieve a notable effect. In an attempt to increase his profits, this man discouraged his partner from revealing his father, Nic\u00e9phore Ni\u00e9pce's, method of creating heliographs. For ten points, identify this Frenchman who developed a namesake process of creating photographic images.", "answer": "Louis <b><u>Daguerre</u></b> (accept Louis-Jacques-Mande <b><u>Daguerre</u></b>; accept <b><u>Daguerre</u></b>otype)  What Englishman, and author of <em>The Pencil of Nature</em>, got into an intellectual property dispute with Louis Daguerre over the invention of Daguerre\u2019s photographic technique?  ANSWER: Henry Fox <b><u>Talbot</u></b> (or William Henry Fox <b><u>Talbot</u></b>)  <b> </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Photography"}, {"question": "<b><u>Student sympathizers of this movement were brutally massacred by the anti-</u><u>leftist death squad known as Grupo Colina during the Barrios Altos Massacre.</u></b> <b><u>Strongman Francisco Morales-Berm\u00fadez's call for open elections in 1980 was</u></b> <b><u>ignored by this political faction, who (+)</u> launched the \"People War\" in the Ayacucho region. The leader of this movement, Abimael [[ah-bee-MAH-ehl]] Guzman, was placed in a cage for public display after his capture by forces loyal to Alberto (*) </b>Fujimori. For ten points, name this Maoist guerilla movement-turned terrorist syndicate of 20th century Peru.", "answer": "<b><u>Shining Path</u></b> (accept <b><u>Sendero Luminoso</u></b>; accept <b><u>Communist Party of Peru</u> </b>before \"Peru\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Before this event, one group involved in it visited the Cattaraugus Reservation</u></b> <b><u>to gain insight into a particular group's societal position. During the second day of</u></b> <b><u>this event, Thomas McClintock read portions of Blackstone\u2019s Commentaries on the</u></b> <b><u>Laws. During this event, (+)</u> Frederick Douglass advocated for the \u201cninth resolution.\u201d Many of this event\u2019s organizers went to the World Anti-Slavery Convention with William Lloyd Garrison. The Declaration of (*) </b>Sentiments was drafted as a result of this event. For ten points, Lucretia Mott and Elizabeth Cady Stanton organized what event to advocate for women\u2019s rights?", "answer": "<b><u>Seneca Falls</u></b> Convention (prompt on \"Women's Rights Convention\" and similar answers before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A conflict named for this body of water was referred to as \u201cthe first serious</u></b> <b><u>nuclear crisis\u201d by U.S. Secretary of State Christian Herter. The Dachen Islands were</u></b> <b><u>seized during a crisis named for this body of water. In 1950, a fleet was sent in by</u></b> <b><u>Harry (+)</u> Truman to \u201cneutralize\u201d this body of water. A third crisis was sparked after missiles were launched in this body of water under the supervision of Lee Teng-hui. (*) </b>For ten points, what \"Strait\" surrounded the territorial disputes between the People\u2019s Republic of China and the Republic of China?", "answer": "<b><u>Taiwan</u></b> Strait (accept <b><u>Formosa</u></b> Strait; accept Strait of <b><u>Fokien</u></b>; accept Strait of <b><u>Fujian</u></b>; accept variations like Strait of <b><u>Taiwan</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The speaker of this oration notes how \u201cthe life of the world may move forward</u></b> <b><u>into broad, sunlit uplands\u201d if a certain result is achieved. This address's speaker</u></b> <b><u>warns that \u201cthe whole fury and might of the enemy must very soon be turned on (+)</u></b> <b>us.\u201d In this speech, the orator claims, \u201cWe in this Island\u2026will never lose our sense of comradeship\u201d and states that a certain sentiment would hold \u201cif the empire lasts a thousand years.\u201d Given two weeks after its speaker had noted that \u201cwe shall (*) </b>fight on the beaches\u201d, for ten points, what was this speech by Winston Churchill about a certain glorious time period?", "answer": "\u201cThis was their <b><u>finest hour</u></b>\" speech (accept Winston <b><u>Churchill</u></b>'s speech on <b><u>June</u></b> <b><u>18, 1940</u></b> before the House of Commons)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>J.B. Vrients was sold a set of plates belonging to a work by Cornelis de Jode</u></b> <b><u>titled for the \u201cMirror of [this place].\" Rhumb lines were used in a 1569 depiction of</u></b> <b><u>this place that was itself inspired by a work known as \u201cTheatre of [this place]\" by</u></b> <b><u>Abraham Ortelius. The \u201cpocket\u201d (+)</u> variety of one type of depiction of this place was popularized amongst elites in the 17th century. Many depictions of this place were made during the Golden Age of Flemish cartography, including the (*) </b>Mercator Projection. For ten points, name this planet depicted on atlases and globes.", "answer": "The <b><u>World</u></b> (or <b><u>Earth</u></b>; accept Orbis <b><u>Terra</u></b>rum; prompt on \u201cglobe\u201d or \u201cmap\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This city was the origin of a movement of upper-middle class teenagers who</u></b> <b><u>came to admire American culture, the Swing Youth. The Star-Club is found in this city,</u></b> <b><u>where one group\u2019s frequent performing caught the attention of Brian (+)</u> Epstein, who was later known as the \u201cFifth\u201d member of that group. Between 1960 and 1962, the Beatles often performed in the Reeperbahn in this city located on the (*) </b>Elbe. For ten points, name this Northern German city.", "answer": "Free and Hanseatic City of <b><u>Hamburg</u></b> (accept Freie und Hansestadt <b><u>Hamburg</u></b>; accept Friee un Hansestadt <b><u>Hamborg</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A temple to this deity was consecrated by Gaius Duilius after the Battle of</u></b> <b><u>Mylae. In Ovid\u2019s</u> </b><em><b><u>Fasti</u></b></em><b><u>, this deity describes himself as the \u201cjanitor of the celestial</u></b> <b><u>court.\u201d Numa Pompilius established a temple at the forum that was dedicated to this</u></b> <b><u>deity. The (+)</u> </b><em><b>rex sacrorum</b></em><b> typically offered a ram to this deity during the Agonium festival. The opening and closing of the gates at this deity\u2019s temple symbolized, respectively, (*) </b>wartime or peace. For ten points, who was this double-faced Roman god of beginnings and transitions?", "answer": "<b><u>Janus</u></b> (or <b><u>Ianus</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>After moving to an all-white suburb of this city, Daisy Myers endured months</u></b> <b><u>of harassment before gaining the nickname \"Rosa Parks of the North.\" Henry Box</u></b> <b><u>Brown shipped himself to freedom in a crate to an Anti-Slavery (+)</u> Society in this city. John Africa founded the Black liberation group MOVE in this city. The Free African Society was called in to deal with a 1793 epidemic of yellow fever in this city, which was treated by Benjamin (*) </b>Rush. For ten points, name this city in which the Declaration of Independence was signed.", "answer": "<b><u>Philadelphia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's participation in the Battle of Boju has been challenged by his</u></b> <b><u>notable absence from the</u> </b><em><b><u>Commentary of Zuo</u></b></em><b><u>. This man was listed as a minister to</u></b> <b><u>King Helu of Wu by Sima Qian [[CHEE-ahn]], and his descendant, (+)</u> Bin, wrote a book with the same title as this man's more famous work. That book by this man includes chapters on \"Attacking with Fire\" and \"The (*)</b> Army on the March.\" For ten points, name this Chinese general and author of <em>The Art of War</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Sun</u></b> Tzu (or <b><u>Sun</u></b> Zi; or <b><u>Sun</u></b> Wu; accept <b><u>Changqing</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}